[Music]
what's up everyone
i hope you are doing great welcome to
episode 14
of the ask a budget show today we talk
about geopolitics
and great power competition so let me
first again define what geopolitics is
geopolitics is a sport it is a sport in
which you make up the rules
as you go along it is a competition for
the
resources and control of the entire
world
so that's what geopolitics is and there
are no rules in it whatever rules apply
to you
are they depend on how powerful you are
and how influential you are and how much
how much resources you can control
so that's what geopolitics is and that's
what we're going to dis
discuss today it's the competition
between the
various great powers of the world and
you have asked me wonderful questions so
let's get right into it
with question number one
so gorangi asks which is the most
important
factor that makes a country a superpower
so the most important factor that makes
a country a superpower is the ability
to project hard power globally on a
global scale
so what's hard power hard power is
military and economic power
and diplomatic power so diplomacy serves
to augment
your military and economic power you
cannot have an efficient
diplomacy without the backing of your
hard power which is the military and
economic power
and economic power can be hard or soft
depending on how you use it
so that is what makes a country makes a
country a superpower
the ability to project hard power on a
global scale
at short notice so you can get things
done
almost immediately when required so as
of today by this definition there's only
one superpower which is the
united states it's the only country that
can project
power globally at a moment's notice
at will and china is the other country
that aspires
to be a superpower it is at present not
able to
project hard power on a global scale but
it aspires to do so it is building the
infrastructure that is required to be
able to do that
so that is the most important factor
that makes a country
a superpower this is an excellent
question to start off with
gorangi again asks what is the place
of india in the power competition
and in what way does our nation do
need to develop to a great extent
so once again let's take the definition
of power
real power national power so national
power is made up of a number of factors
it's called comprehensive national power
it takes into account the kind of
leadership you have
the kind of governance structure you
have
the military power at your disposal the
economic power at your disposal
the kind of alliances you have and all
that so all of that
is taken together a measure of your
comprehensive national power
also the kind of natural resources you
have and access to resources
and all of that so that makes up your
comprehensive national power
now in the power competition what really
matters
is your ability to project hard power
beyond your boundaries
so let's take a look at our map the map
is our best tool
it's our best friend for understanding
things so this here
is the map of the indian
of india and its surrounding regions so
let's
ask ourselves how far is india
able to project hard power economic
and military power beyond its borders
let's go west can india project power in
pakistan
not really forget about afghanistan it's
too far
it's cut off from those places what
about central asia
india doesn't really have much influence
there and no means of really
projecting hard power tibet used to be
in the indo sphere
now it is part of china india has no
influence there whatsoever
nepal bhutan well so so nepal and bhutan
are both
nepal is very much leaning towards china
and india has done nothing to stop that
bhutan is again being encroached by
china and india is not really able to
help it
out when it comes to myanmar i think
there's a lot of chinese influence there
bangladesh well bangladesh and india's
relations are not
well not not great not bad but not great
either
what about other countries in south east
asia india hardly has a presence
sri lanka we know the situation with sri
lanka the fishermen that sri lanka keeps
capturing or sometimes even shooting to
death and the maldives well
maldives in india have had a fraught
history in recent times
so as you can see india doesn't really
have the ability to project real
power beyond its borders at least
on the land borders india has the golden
opportunity to
to basically make the indian ocean
region this entire vast region of ocean
its own india can do it india still has
the opportunity
but to do that you need to have a strong
navy you need to have a blue water navy
so much of the global shipping trade
goes on through indian waters so for
example when you when
uh trade when ships are coming through
the suez canal
and through the gulf of aden they passed
through india's lakshadweep islands
okay over here in order to go eastwards
so they passed through basically indian
territory indian waters
and even while going towards the strait
of malacca over here
they again pass through the andaman
islands
so india basically has the potential
ability
to control global shipping and global
trade just by having us
an and so and and good navy
you know a proper blue water navy so
india keeps saying that uh
the indian ocean region is our strategic
backyard
but slogans don't make it yourself a
strategic backyard you need to take
action
if india were to develop a navy a proper
navy like 300 ships strong
which means at least 100 ships can be
deployed at any given time
then the entire power equations of the
indian ocean region
and much of the world would change
instantaneously and india would be taken
seriously as a significant global power
as
it stands today india is basically
at best a regional power that too only
because of its size not because it's
able to influence
its neighbors so that is the situation
as of today india is a potential
superpower i keep saying that
india can become a significant global
player in just 10 years time
if it would basically develop its hard
power hard power
is economic strength and military
strength economic strength
is being developed to some extent
military strength is being completely
neglected
as we speak right now so these are all
factors that go
come into the picture that all are put
together in calculating
a country's actual standing on the scale
of power
in the global level so as of today india
doesn't really project power
i think israel and iran project power
beyond their borders much more than
india do
these tiny little nations are much more
active on a global geopolitical scale
or at least a regional geopolitical
scale beyond their borders
than india ever does so it's all a
question about of attitude
and ambition right now india seems to
lack it but india has the potential to
very quickly very quickly become a
genuine
global player on the geopolitical arena
so that's where india stands as of today
but things can change if certain steps
are taken
okay advaith asks what is japan's role
and significance in this power play as
it has one of the most efficient human
resource managements
in the world yes you are right in japan
uh is one of the most optimized
countries in the world it has one of the
most efficient
systems of governance and business and
it was
one of the best industries industrial
ecosystems in the world
it has the best cutting edge research
and
development japan is considered to be a
shadow nuclear power which means it can
it doesn't have nuclear weapons but it
can have nuclear weapons next week if it
wants to
and it can have delivery systems too
next week if it wants to
so that's the level of technological
advancement japan has
but as as things stand today
let's take a look at the the map of
japan
so here we are let's go towards japan
this is where japan stands
so japan occupies a very interesting and
significant position
in the geography of asia it essentially
cuts off much of the pacific from
china because japan goes all the way to
these islands here you know
okinawa etc all the way to taiwan
so that's one of the island chains that
china is always so concerned about
so japan occupies a very uh
strategically
important location geographically
japan is a pacifistic country it
has a small armed small army
an armed force so to say they call it
the defense forces
so since the second world war ended
japan has been
basically militarily very inactive very
dormant it does maintain a military
it does have a reasonably good navy as
well
but the entire focus of its armed forces
is on defense there is no
offensive uh well it has never taken any
offensive
attitude ever in the past 70 plus years
so japan is a significant power
but it doesn't project power beyond its
borders
even if you look at japan's economic
policies
can also be a means of projecting power
beyond your boundaries beyond your
borders
but if you look at the way japan
conducts itself economically
and the way china conducts itself
economically you would say china is
intent on an ever-ending expansion and
projection of power
using all means including economic means
which is one of the very
important components in china's foreign
policy
whereas japan does not indulge in the
kind of economic practices
and trade practices and mercantile
practices that china does
japan does not try to beggar its
neighbors it doesn't indulge in
mercantilism
it doesn't try to lay debt traps on its
neighbors
it essentially indulges in fair trade
practices
more or less i can't say all of these
practices would be good
but if you compare the two it's a
difference between heaven and hell
black and white so japan does it doesn't
have the ambition
to be a global geopolitical player it is
content to be
a peaceful and developed country
and to live in peace and let others live
in peace how long that will last while
it all depends on china's
attitude china has a big grudge against
japan
and because of the events of the second
world war in china
always uses these historical pretexts to
bully other nations
so there is a ongoing land dispute
between territorial dispute between
china and japan and china has been
bullying japan in various
ways for a long time so japan is a
significant economy it is one of the
most technologically advanced nations
but it is not a global power player on
the geopolitical
scene because of its pacifistic
constitution and because it is
defense oriented it has a very strong
navy
fyi its navy is more powerful than
india's navy
significantly more powerful than india's
navy what is the measure of
navy's strength so
most people answer the number of ships a
navy has
that's a wrong answer the strength of
your navy doesn't depend on how many
ships you have
the strength of your navy is directly
proportional to how many
missiles you can deploy at sea on a
given day
and the japanese navy can deploy more
than a thousand missiles on
any given day so at right right now as
we speak it has at least a thousand
missiles deployed at sea right this
moment
maybe more maybe 1500 or more so that is
the strength of the japanese navy
the strength the power of a navy is
measured in the number of
missiles anti-ship and other missiles it
can
deploy at any given time so japan's navy
is much more powerful than india's navy
its submarine strength is very good it
has very very advanced submarines
so these are factors that that china is
very off
but as i said japan's entire outlook is
defensive in nature
as of today and that's why it is not a
very big
player on the geopolitical scene even
though it can become one if it chooses
to or if it is
allowed to by its overlord
which we will come into which we will
get into uh you know in a few moments
so that's where japan stands uh that's
where japan
stands in the global power
power play position
okay pink line cabs asks
how does how does a small country like
how has a small country like israel
made a dominance like this but the whole
arab world has not been successful
that's a great question we haven't
really discussed israel much
until now so let's talk about israel as
always
we take a look at the map okay
okay let's go westwards from india let's
go to the middle east
and to the mediterranean region the
eastern mediterranean
so this here is israel the nation of
israel
and as you can see every single
neighboring country is its enemy they
all
want israel to be gone they want israel
to disappear from the map
they want to erase this nation from the
map this tiny little
desert nation it's not a desert nation
but yeah
so they they all want israel to be
erased from the map
and still here it is israel is still
there
and the question is
the question is how is a small country
like israel able to be so dominant
but the arab world has not been
successful so the
reason israel has succeeded and
prospered and thrived is first of all
because of help from the west a small
country like this
with so few resources
cannot survive on its own unless it gets
external help
now israel is a very powerful
and influential and politically active
to some extent jewish diaspora across
the world
especially in the western world
especially in the united states
so the united states has been a very
strong ally of the israelis
over the ever since israel was was
recreated
in the 1940s so the americans have
propped up israel to a great deal the
british have also helped israel
nowadays there are political problems
between israel and the us
obama was very very uh he was very
antagonistic to netanyahu and israel
in general and the democrats have
usually have of
in recent times been not favorably
inclined towards israel but historically
the united states has supported israel
to a great deal
in terms of financial support or or
military support transfer of certain a
sale of certain military items
etc and the other thing is that israel
is an extremely resourceful country
so uh the israelis have
always had this siege mentality and you
can't blame them for it because they are
surrounded on all sides by enemies
they have fought numerous wars etc so
they
basically the entire adult population of
israel is
basically their professional soldiers
they all undergo
proper military training they all serve
as soldiers
and they are all ready to serve in the
armed forces at a moment's notice
and israel has a very powerful
security service intelligence services
the so-called mossad
and the shinbeth etc which
enables israel to project power
essentially at a global scale
to some extent uh it can target
forces that are that are antagonistic
towards israel anywhere in the world
so they have proven this they have
demonstrated this time and time again
operation entebbe
and the the abduction of uh
of adolf aikman from argentina in the
1960s or 70s
60s most likely etc so they are able to
project power globally
and they they are technologically very
advanced they've ensured
their their industries and technologies
are very advanced
they have this uh startup culture they
have this entrepreneurial culture
you know they encourage all that a lot
and they have ensured that they develop
the best technology
so these are the factors that have
enabled israel
to uh to stay uh independent to stay
to ward of the enemies and let me also
mention the most important factor israel
has nuclear weapons
israel is a nuclear it's an undeclared
nuclear weapon state
it has had nuclear weapons for many
decades it has never officially
uh declared this but it is uh it's an
open secret
so that is uh one of the major factors
that if israel comes under mortal threat
if it is
under threat of being overrun by the
enemy it will
use nuclear weapons as a last resort so
these are the factors
that have ensured that israel not only
stays independent stays stays secure
but also thrives so that is the reason
why israel is doing well and why are the
arabs not doing well because
well the first thing is that the entire
uh
middle east it's always under crisis
right the middle east crisis has been
going on for decades
well it's the western powers to some
extent that have
ensured that this region is always under
crisis so that
they are able to project power there and
interfere
and uh basically uh
basically control the various actions of
various governments by playing sides etc
so that is one reason and the arab
nations are essentially
basically these are artificially created
nations the borders that you see today
are artificially drawn borders
uh this was all once under the ottoman
empire and then under the british empire
and various countries were controlled by
various uh western powers
and when they left the region they drew
these arbitrary boundaries
so these boundaries will change over
time
as boundaries naturally do so things
will eventually
someday come to some sort of of balance
or equilibrium
so that is the reason why the all these
arabic countries and the basically the
entire islamic world is always
divided and in a state of turmoil
this is the legacy of colonialism and
the legacy of their internal divides and
all that
it's a very complicated story but to a
great extent it's been fomented
and kept going by the west to a great
extent
and that is also the reason why israel
has been supported so much by the west
to keep this entire
middle east cold on boiling
so that's how geopolitics is played
power projection
okay this is by vandit singh the
equation of russia and turkey has been a
complex one to understand they both
stand on opposite sides in syria libya
et cetera they collaborate militarily
and strategically despite of turkey
being a nato member
explain this in context of the age old
rivalry of the ottomans in the russian
empire where does the u.s and india
stand to gain lose
with regards to this frenemy kind of
relationship between the turks
and the russians so like you said the
turks and the russians
have an old rivalry during the ottoman
empire these were two rivals
the russians the russian empire versus
the ottoman empire there was a great
competition it was kind of part of the
great game russia
and the uk were playing playing in in
central asia
so it kind of spilled over to some
extent between turkey and
and and the between the ottoman empire
and the russian empire
so if you look at the map once again
if you will see turkey if you go north
of turkey you reach
you have the to the east you have the
caucasus region
and in the north you have ukraine and
crimea etc so it's all basically
uh regions of russian dominance and
russian territories
so russia and turkey and the ottoman
empire have been antagonists
for a great deal of time in the 1920s i
believe or 1910s
the russians even invaded parts of
turkey and reached almost all the way to
istanbul just
a few miles from istanbul and they were
stopped by the other western forces etc
so there's always been this fraught
relationship yeah
a relationship of that contests uh
shared space so as of today like you
said russia
sorry turkey is a nato ally it's an
official nato ally
and yet turkey the geopolitical
ambitions of turkey are basically
oversized
they uh under erdogan they aspire to
revive
kind of in a way the ottoman empire
turkey aspires to be a great power again
it wants to project power much beyond
its its borders
so it's trying to buy influence and
acquire influence in various parts of
the world especially in its immediate
neighborhood
now if you go to the west of turkey in
if you go to the west you have greece
bulgaria the balkans romania et cetera
so these are all christian countries
or used to be christian mostly until
very recently
so turkey can't hope to have much
influence there
but if you go east of turkey you will
find all the basically the
islamic countries the countries that
were once under the ottoman empire
even north africa is all islamic so
turkey sees that
as a great fertile ground for projecting
power and expanding its influence
and that's turkey's overall ambition to
revive its great imperial days and that
essentially
clashes with nato's ambition of u.s
supremacy
nato has one function only to maintain
and preserve
and expand to some extent u.s supreme
supremacy and hegemony
across across the region of europe so
turkey's ambitions clash with that they
are at cross purposes
so that's why turkey is increasingly
being alienated from nato
they are buying russian missile systems
the s-400 system
which nato disapproves of that's why
they have refused to sell the
f-35 fighter jet to the turks and the
turks are fine with that
so turkey and russia now seem to be
having some kind of rapprochement
some kind of they are growing closer
together
even though they do clash at times
turkey in a couple of
two three years ago shot down a russian
jet killed a couple of russian fire
russian pilots or at least one fighter
fighter pilot
and yet wherever their interests align
they are cooperating
because russia also seeks to maintain a
sphere of influence
which is beyond its borders so russia
sees the central asian republics
kazakhstan uh
georgia etc it sees this region as part
of its natural sphere of influence
and turkey also sees these turkic
central asian neighbors kazakhstan
uzbekistan turkmenistan etc as part of
its natural sphere of influence
so there is a conflict there but there
is a scope for cooperation
for now temporarily also
even azerbaijan so that is the situation
right now this is a
temporary
temporary convergence of interests
turkey and russia
are likely to remain long-term rivals
but temporarily they are cooperating
wherever they can because
turkey is slowly drifting away from nato
and from the u.s
and the russians basically their biggest
threat is the u.s because the us is
essentially
surrounding russia with with various
military bases and
pointing this as missiles at russia
so that's why as of now right now their
interests converge to some extent so
they are cooperating
and that is the nature of geopolitics
there are no permanent enemies there are
no permanent allies
there are only temporary alliances and
temporary adversaries
so right now like you said russia and
turkey are frenemies
but this is not a long term arrangement
this is a temporary fleeting transient
arrangement
and we shall see how it goes how does it
affect the united states well the united
states is not happy with the way
turkey is drifting away from its orbit
and what does india stand to gain well
india doesn't really
have any power projection ambitions or
plans or any presence in this region
so india doesn't really stand to gain
much or lose much
of course if turkey gets more powerful
and because pakistan and turkey are
natural allies it will be
problematic for india so to that extent
it could be problematic for india as
well because india and turkey
traditionally have been on opposite
sides of the table
uh never allies never really uh
culturally
culturally or any other way aligned in
any manner so basically turkey and india
you could say our have always been in a
mild state of hostility or antagonism
turkey has always supported pakistan
especially of late
so in that to that extent it is not good
for india
but all india needs to do start exerting
its own
strength and influence abroad to change
things
so that's where things stand as of today
vis-a-vis the relationship of russia and
turkey
okay arjun asks do you think china will
be the next
soviet union means will it collapse due
to communism
i have heard many chinese are unhappy
with the current current government
you see china is not a communist nation
china says it's a communist marxist
socialist nation etc
but the truth is that it's an out and
out capitalist
nation it's fully capitalistic in
in nature it has billionaires a chinese
billionaire is born every other day and
a chinese billionaire dies of some
reason
every 15 or 20 days that's what's
happening in china right now
so china is completely fully
capitalistic
right it's a full it's it's trying to
industrialize fully
it doesn't really it is socialism is
just lip service marxism communism is
just lip service
it's basically the rule of one party
it's an imperial state
so it's basically reverted to the
traditional chinese form of governance
which is the imperial system
xi jinping may be called the president
or whatever but is actually the emperor
and the ccp the chinese communist party
is the current ruling dynasty
so it doesn't mean that sri jinping's
daughter will become the next premier
but somebody from the ccp in the future
after xi jinping
will succeed him as the president if
everything goes according to plan
if the ccp remains in power uh for a
long period of time
so it is basically the country has
reverted to the imperial system with
certain changes
so it is not by any means a communist
nation
will it collapse well only time will
tell uh
typically i the chinese dynasties
collapse when they suffer a military
defeat or they lose
a face in some manner in the eyes of
their subjects
so that's when widespread rebellion
happens and when
1.4 billion people rebel there's nothing
even the ccp can do about it
so that will happen only if the chinese
communist party has
is seen to have lost its divine mandate
to rule the mandate of heaven so there's
this concept in china called the mandate
of heaven every emperor
has the mandate of heaven as long as he
or she as long as he essentially
is able to control the country tightly
no matter how many atrocities they
commit to the people
as long as they are able to control the
country and and
basically that is the only criterion for
having the mandate of heaven
but if they suffer a catastrophic
military defeat somewhere
it means that they have lost the mandate
of heaven and that's when the dynasty
inevitably crumbles and falls and then
there is a dynastic cycle
there's a period of upheaval and strife
and eventually after some
time a new dynasty emerges so as of
today that ccp is very secure
but if it does indulge in some military
misadventure somewhere
and it suffers a catastrophic defeat
that it may trigger
off a chain of events that may cause its
collapse so it will not collapse because
it is
it is a communist regime it is not a
communist regime it will not collapse
because the people are unhappy with it
people have always been unhappy in china
there's never been a benevolent uh
imperial imperial dynasty ever
so that the only way the ccp will will
fall from power if it
is if it it indulges in some military
misadventure
and suffers a catastrophic defeat even
if it's a small defeat
if it is very visible then it could be
curtains
so that's how things go in china
akash asks what should be india's
strategy to
to tackle china and pakistan
individually
so so in the past many
indian leaders and prime ministers
have said that it is india's it is in
india's interest to have a strong and
stable and prosperous pakistan
well that is nonsense a strong and
stable and prosperous pakistan will
always be used
by china as a proxy against india and as
a destabilizing force on our western
boundary
what india needs see basically pakistan
is indian territory which was given up
against
without consulting the people so i
regard
pakistan as as unfinished business
it is indian territory which will
eventually in the long run
be reintegrated with the mother nation
as of now pakistan is an antagonistic
power
it is not powerful in its own right it
is powerful because it is propped up by
the chinese
what india needs to do in the immediate
future 5 10 20 years maximum
is ensure that china that pakistan is
balkanized
so we need to ensure that the various
independence movements
and freedom struggles within pakistan
and there are many many of these
and these are very justifiable because
people have been oppressed brutally for
decades in pakistan it's a horrible
place
it's a terrible place to live in and
it's a one-party rule
it's the it's the army that rules the
country
the so-called prime minister is just a
puppet it's just a punching bag
so india needs to encourage this and
india needs to
engineer peacefully
you know peacefully a peaceful
and democratic balkanization of pakistan
sindh should become independent
balochistan
punjab northern areas can reintegrate
with afghanistan
and kashmir should return to its home
country its homeland
etc so that's what needs to happen
gilgamesh
and pok should return where they belong
and once this happens then we can deal
with each of these independent regions
independently nicely kindly and we can
help them out
and slowly over time we can reintegrate
them so this should be the immediate
objective next 10 20 years maximum
we can't wait longer than that when it
comes to
china india's objective should be to
liberate tibet from china
now this is not a short-term process it
will not
it will not happen in the next 10 years
right china is too powerful right now
india is too weak
india has no military strength to speak
of we have an enormous army
the strength of your army doesn't depend
on the number of soldiers you have my
friends
your soldiers may be the bravest
soldiers in the world it
matters not at all 1962 also we have the
bravest soldiers in the world
what matters is the equipment the
infrastructure that
and the technology and the hardware
it all depends on the hardware the
technology
and the kind and that's what matters the
the quality of your heart how brave you
are doesn't matter anymore in warfare
so that's what india needs to enhance
india needs to invest in its armed
forces
and one day maybe we should give
ourselves a 10 20 year
time limit we can basically engineer the
freedom of tibet from illegal
and brutal chinese occupation so if we
can do that then
india's northern northern border will
again be peaceful it will again be an
as a culture that is basically the same
as our culture it will be people who are
basically very friendly towards us
we could if tibet was free we could even
have open borders with them
the way we have with nepal so all the
border problems would go away
if that would that were to happen so
that should be the objective
vis-a-vis china and pakistan with china
it's all about tibet with pakistan it's
all about basically
uh helping these independence movements
out because these are
these are valid independence movements
that
this is an artificial nation it has no
business existing
right pakistan has never existed before
1947 there was no nation of pakistan
there was no concept of pakistan even
today pakistan is an artificial nation
it doesn't have an identity and culture
of its own it's all borrowed
so this nation has no business existing
it is indian territory
and we need to engineer peacefully
in the best optimum way possible it's
slow but steady reintegration into india
and the starting process is to balkanize
it peacefully
so that's what india needs to do
vis-a-vis pakistan and
china
okay sunny negi asks what do you think
about the freedom struggle going on in
balochistan since 1948 after pakistan
annexed it should india back the
balochis
yes absolutely india should back the
balochistan freedom movement
india should ensure that balochistan
gets freedom
from the pakistani occupation
balochistan was a free nation
and the pakistanis under jinnah or
invaded
and occupied it and annexed the nation
and the
indian government did not even raise an
eyebrow
so india needs to ensure that
balochistan gets freedom from
this tyrannical oppressive pakistani
occupation
they are essentially murdering the
balochis they they are
marginalizing the balochis and
extracting
all the resources from the land it's a
resource-rich region
it's also a wonderful maritime region it
is a nice
port called guadar which basically was
was offered to india by the sultan of
oman and india refused it so it went to
pakistan
so india needs to support the
balochistan
freedom struggle it is a just freedom
struggle
india needs to ensure that balochistan
is liberated or they are able to
liberate themselves
from pakistan and india will run into
opposition from iran as well because
part of balochistan is currently in iran
the iranians have also occupied the
western region of balochistan
so if the eastern region were to become
free there would be the same sentiment
in the iranian occupied portion of
balochistan
which will be a story for another day so
it's complicated but yes
india should support the aspirations
the democratic and freedom
aspirations of the balochi people
okay this is by sapi sir um
china has become a powerful country to
reckon with
yes all that so if one day india becomes
an economic powerhouse like the us and
china
is there a possibility of these western
countries plus the u.s
treating india treating us the same way
they are treating china yes this is a
wonderful question brilliant question
so see here's the thing about nato and
the us alliances
the objective of these alliances
of nato or any other alliance the u.s
has the five
i's alliance or any other alliance the
objective
is simple it has a one-point agenda
to ensure that u.s the united states
remains
the primary superpower the only
hegemonic force in the world
it is to ensure the continuity
of u.s supremacy and hegemony
that's all that's a one point agenda it
only serves the u.s in the long run
yes it does throw some crumbs at his
allies etc
but even when it comes to the five ice
alliance the five
anglo-saxon nations the united states
canada the uk
australia and new zealand so these are
five nations with the same ethnic
structure
the ethnic origin and the uh the
geographical origin the uk
even in this alliance which is
supposedly the closest alliance at all
five
eyes even in this alliance the us treats
every other country
as a junior partner uh in the 1990s or
2000s i believe the u.s
sold some fighter aircraft to the
australians
and the australians found that they
could not use them to target
anything except what the u.s wanted them
to so the
code inside the computers of this
fighter plane
would not allow australians to target
certain uh certain targets
they would need to take permission from
the americans to do that so basically
these fighter planes that were sold to
the australians were basically useless
so that's how they treat even their
closest allies
and then the australians had to
re-engineer the entire computer code
in order to make the planes work and be
actual
owners of the plane of these aircraft
these f-16s i think or f-18s i'm not
sure
one of those two so the united states
will not
ever tolerate any country
trying to rise to its level and and the
strange thing is that the rise of china
is all thanks to the us it's an
enormous strategic blunder on the part
of richard nixon
and henry kissinger so they thought they
could
prop china up against the ussr in
another episode i had spoken about the
fact that china and the ussr nearly went
to war
the the soviets had actually considered
very seriously
nuking the chinese it was kissinger it
was nixon who intervened
and threatened the russians with a
reprisal if they were to nuke china
and that's how the they saved china and
then they had this
diplomacy with the chinese and they
agreed to support china's
industrialization process
in the hope they they they naively
believed that if china were
to become stronger more industrialized
and more more prosperous
then it would naturally become a
democracy how
how naive and foolish that sounds today
but it is the americans that have
basically
helped china rise to where it is today
china would never have risen to where it
is today
if it would not for american support
throughout the decades
since the 1970s since the late 1960s and
early 1970s
so today america has risen has woken up
to the fact that china
is potentially an existential threat for
them and therefore they are doing
everything they can to some extent
to some extent to to
slow the chinese rise down if india were
to try
and rise to that level it would invite
similar if not harsher reactions
from the united states and from the
entire
western world which is essentially well
it is essentially run and managed by the
united states
so yes they would treat us not the way
they treat in china they would treat us
worse than they treat china because
india is not a strong military power
or strong economic power comparable to
china india's economy is much
smaller than chinese china's economy
india doesn't have the economic networks
and all the alliances
and all the dependencies of other
countries the way china has china has
been systematically building this up
since the 1980s so even when china was a
small
impoverished economy it was still
thinking like a global power
it was planning to be a global power
step by step by step
so that is what india lacks but if india
were to aspire to do that
if india were to take steps to do that
it would invite
similar responses from the us and from
the west
and you see this all the time india is
slowly
uh rising as an economy and
in some other ways and you can see the
hostile reaction of the western media
towards india
it's like hostile across the board they
try and focus on only the negatives they
try and
portray india in an extremely negative
manner so you see that
all the time anyway so if india were to
really start rising
then god forbid you know the the
reactions will be much harsher
so that is is the truth
okay priya samantha asks explain
nagaland's insurgency why
are most nagas christian so this is
about india but it is very much related
to geopolitics
and therefore let's let's take a look at
this
so my dear friends do you know what
nagaland is
i have found that many indians don't
know anything about the northeast of
india so
so just assuming that our education
system has not provided you with this
context
let me do that so here we are back to
india let's go into the eastern region
of india
this is the so called north east of
india over here you have
bangladesh here you have myanmar or
burma
this here is basically chinese occupied
territory
to the north you have tibet which is
chinese occupied territory
so this is the northeast of india to the
north you have arunachal pradesh
here you have assam and here we have
nagaland
so nagaland is a state
it's a region that has seen constant
insurgency for decades
and like you said it's a christian state
it's a christian insurgency
so let's go into the history of this
region a little bit
so people in india the majority think of
nagaland
as related to the mythical naga people
of the mahabharata
that is not so the people of nagaland
are not related to the naga people
of the mahabharata era not at all
this is a new term the british created
so here's the truth about the people of
nagaland they are not one ethnicity
they are not one people it's a diverse
array of tribes
who don't even speak each other's
language who don't
even worship the same gods they don't
even have the same culture
it's all it's a diverse fragmented bunch
of tribes who have nothing to do with
each other
some of them can't even speak each
other's language the only thing they
have in common
is a foreign religion they were all
christianized during the british
occupation of india
and the british occupation of the
northeast and they were further
christianized
during jawaharlal nehru's regime when he
invited
american missionaries to so-called
civilize
the people of of this region so this
term
nagas was given by the british to give
these people a common
unifying ethnicity it's a made-up
ethnicity
they are not one people the only thing
that unites them today
is this religion so basically nagaland
the entire insurgency
is propped up by foreign powers
there are photographs on the internet
you will you can search for them of
naga terrorists and insurgent leaders on
the great wall of china
okay so they they have been very much
uh supported by the chinese they have
been funded by the chinese
and they've been trained by the chinese
they have been provided weaponry and
equipment
and arms and emulation by the chinese
across the border as you can see there
is this border
uh the border with china is not far away
so the chinese used to and still do
ferry arms ammunition cache etc across
northern burma into nagaland and chinese
pies have been captured you know
in nagaland and in northeast india
so this is not one ethnicity it's an
artificial ethnicity
they have nothing in common most of them
with each other the only thing in common
is christianity and the other force that
is unifying nagaland and
fueling the insurgency is the west
wired by means of various christian
organizations
right so you will see these websites and
facebook groups
run by various naga or sudo naga
organizations they talk about nagaland
as being
in a country in southeast asia that's
occupied by india
right that sort of thing so this entire
thing is basically to destabilize india
china wants india to be destabilized the
west also
to a great extent wants india to be
destabilized so the west
and china have converged in nagaland to
fuel this insurgency it's been going on
for decades
even today the nagas have a de facto
government of their own they want to
have their own flag
they have their own armed forces which
are not part of the indian army
you know and that's the sort of thing we
have so it's and they
they impose their own taxes on the
people that don't don't go into the
indian state
right and many times in the past
during the tenure of mr chidambaram as
home minister etc
the nagas imposed land blockades on
manipur
so they prevented goods from reaching
manipur which caused incredible
shortages
these blockades lasted for many many
months
at a time it's incredible inside india
one state imposing economic blockade and
economic sanctions
on another state and no one came to know
about this the media never
reported this so this is the kind of
role that nagaland is playing as of
today
it is it is being all orchestrated from
outside of india
and the naga issue is the one problem
that is uh basically preventing india
from reaching out to the
rest of southeast asia because india
wants to build
roads road connections between manipur
from mori et cetera where is mori
here is the town of mori so more is
supposed to be the gateway to south east
asia
for india there will be a road
connecting more
all the way to to yangon and all the way
down south to singapore
that's the plan and even a railway line
which will connect
manipur and the other parts of southeast
asia
so that's the plan it's been there for
decades and because of this naga
insurgency it's not coming to fruition
so india needs to solve this naga issue
it india needs to cut off these
external influences in nagaland we have
to understand this naga ethnicity does
not even exist it's a fake ethnicity
it's a number of tribes
if they were not christianized they were
all polytheistic tribes and they would
all be considered to be hindus they
would all consider themselves
to be hindus the way the tribes of
arunachal consider themselves to be
hindus
but today even arunachal is being
christianized so these are all
foreign influences these are not
religious influences these are
all tools of geopolitical coercion
so that is the game that's been played
in the northeast
uh rapid in influx of foreign
culture even foreign migrants etc
it's a very complicated thing but india
needs to get its uh
get its act together especially in
nagaland
this cannot be allowed to go on for too
long i think things are much better now
compared to 10 years ago
when nagaland was imposing these
blockades on manipur
so i think it's being handled to some
extent right now
maybe it's a longer process so let's
wait and watch but that
is the truth about nagaland
and it's a brief history of what's been
going on there
okay debbie asks why is china picking up
conflicts everywhere at the same time
what was the
intent behind the galwan intentions it
looked well thought out what did they
accomplish
china is china has basically uh
territorial disputes with almost all of
its neighbors
if you look at the nation of china
it has it claims part parts of mongolia
it has already absorbed the so-called
inner mongolia it wants more
it has territorial conflicts with with
every other nation that you see over
here with kyrgyzstan with kazakhstan
with tajikistan
with afghanistan with everybody
everybody even with uh
with myanmar with bhutan with
nepal to some extent and
with the japanese so basically they are
trying to keep every single neighbor
off balance maybe they will
someday hope be hoping to acquire the
territory in the future
but the main intention right now is to
keep every neighbor destabilized to keep
bullying each neighbor to do this this
salami slicing you take
little slices of territory one at a time
a few meters here a few meters there
you just keep slicing away you keep
doing this pin pricks and you keep the
neighbor off balance at all times
that is their strategy galwan was part
of that they were getting really
aggressive
and they got something they did not
basically they did not
expect they got a bloody nose uh a
whole bunch of the soldiers were killed
many more soldiers than indians died
so that was a very big wake-up call for
them and as you can see after galway
nothing has happened
probably because they were accomplished
a lot more with their virus
than they could have accomplished with
border disputes or wars
but that is the intention behind all of
their border conflicts and all of those
conflicts
and the reason they have kept the border
with india undemarcated
is so that they can keep on exerting
pressure on india
and keep on bullying india so india will
never have a settled northern boundary
and in the future at a time of their
choosing they can try and do more
incursions or try to nibble away at more
territory
so that is the entire modus operandi of
the chinese
and that's what india has to contend
with that's what every neighbor of china
has to contend with so galwan was a
disaster
a small scale disaster they tried to
cover it up
you know so they did not accomplish what
they intended to accomplish they
intended to keep pushing india back
back but this time india fought back and
punched them on the nose and gave them a
very bloody nose
so it was something they did not expect
at all and now they are recalibrating
their strategy but overall the strategy
is still the same
to keep biting away to keep nibbling
away and keep the neighbors
off balance at all times
this is a good question how did japan
become
one of the best friends of the western
countries especially the usa
even after the us nuked them during
world war
ii this is a great question right how
did that happen
today japan is very much in the in the
sphere of the western world
it's a to some extent a westernized
country it has a very very strong
alliance with the us
so how did this happen so
what really happened is that japan
came under u.s occupation the united
states
defeated japan the japanese surrendered
after being nuked twice
the united states took over the whole
country of japan the administration of
japan all the military bases of japan
they took over the whole country they
occupied the country
then the japanese constitution the meiji
constitution
was rewritten under the supervision of
general douglas macarthur
and the new constitution post-war
consideration was put in place which was
basically authored by the americans
and that constitution is enforced today
it has not been changed
once since the time the americans
supervised it okay and japan
is still under u.s occupation
let me demonstrate that so let's take a
look at our trusty old map
let's go towards japan so this here is
japan
the americans have dozens
of military bases in japan let me show
you
one or two of these let me show you one
of these so
this here is the island of okinawa the
home of okinawa karate
karate so this island has
a large number of usbs let's let's look
into this
so if we go here we have let's take a
look at the actual satellite image
so this is clearly an airport in
airstrip
it says mcas futenma
let's see what it means marine
corps air station u.s
united states armed forces base
so this is an american base on japanese
soil
does a sovereign nation ever allow a
permanent base of another country on its
soil
especially dozens of these no
there are many more but i've just shown
you one and that should be enough
for the purpose of this illustration
so my point is that the country of japan
is under u.s occupation even today
right it is managed by the us it is
well it is said to have an a strong
alliance with the u.s
but it's actually under u.s occupation
de facto u.s occupation
even germany today to some extent is
under de facto u.s occupation
so that is the true story which was the
question this is the question yes
so after the japanese were nuked by the
u.s the country was taken over by the us
it was occupied by the us and it is
still under u.s occupation
and that's how it appears to have become
the best friend of the western countries
the japanese have made the best of the
situation
they have become an extremely well
developed country
the most technical technologically
advanced nation in the world
they have a reasonably strong uh armed
forces they have a
reasonable they have a quite strong navy
as well but it's all under u.s
supervision
so that's the truth of the matter
okay what will happen to countries what
will happen to countries in the middle
east when we completely switch over to
sustainable sources of power
well the only income source in the
middle east is oil most people don't
even work
most people just pretend to work there
are some jobs etc in saudi arabia
but you don't really have to work there
everything is subsidized oil is
basically free
but now that other sources of energy are
becoming slowly gradually mainstreamed
but the saudis and the other middle
eastern countries are beginning to feel
the pinch
so they are trying to make uh future
plans contingency plans
about what happens when that free money
kind of dries up because the entire boom
that you have seen in the middle east
all these
beautiful glittering cities and all it's
all because of the oil boom it's all
because of free money that came from oil
that basically pours out of the ground
so they have done nothing they have done
no work
to actually earn all this it's just been
the blessings of
of the gods so when the world
starts switching over more and more to
other sources of fuel
to other sources of power it's going to
be crisis time for the middle east
the region will go deeper into
instability
and it's going to be an interesting time
so you know
this prosperity that they are enjoying
will not last forever
and it is now a matter of time before
their their free
free income drive starts drying up so
the next
20 30 years will be very interesting for
the middle east it's going to be a
very turbulent time in the middle east
interesting
anusha asks with india's foreign policy
alignment to the towards the us
has it sacrificed india's erstwhile
allies like russia and iran
is this also one of the reasons for
china's aggression towards india
well i would beg to disagree first of
all
iran was never an ally of india iran has
always supported pakistan
at least softly when it comes to
pakistan's conflicts with india
there was one of the wars was it 65 most
likely 65
when the pakistanis flew all of their
fighter planes to iran
in order to safeguard them from indian
bombardment so the iranians allowed this
so they took the side of pakistan in
this
conflict in this war with india they
called bush in java affair
the man our man was kidnapped from iran
from iranian soil and he was handed over
to the pakistanis
so iran has never been an ally of india
it's always
well we have had reasonably okay
relationships with a relationship with
them
because we we wanted their oil we needed
their oil
and they were also in dire straits
economically because of various
sanctions
that's why they valued india as a
regular buyer of oil and that's why the
relationship has been cordial
and oakish but it's never been an ally
as far as russia is concerned the ussr
was basically india's
patron state during the cold war india
was a satellite state of the ussr
it was never an ally it was a client and
customer relationship
the ussr was the senior partner senior
partner the
in india was a junior partner it was the
it
held the begging ball to the soviets and
the soviets gave us various crumbs
and india's economy crawled along
the the so-called the much derided
so-called
offensive term the hindu rate of growth
which is actually the neheruvian rate of
growth
so it so after the second after the cold
war
ended after the ussr collapsed the
relationship between india and russia
changed drastically russia lost much of
its geopolitical influence it lost much
of its hard power
it became economically almost destitute
so it was in no position to help india
in
any way whatsoever and the relationship
changed completely
that in ancient uh that old
what you call alliance no longer existed
and it became a transactional
relationship
so today it's no longer in any way an
alliance india and russia still trust
each other to some extent
there is a very cordial relationship
between the two leaders
and between the bureaucracies the
foreign affairs
ministries etc but these two nations are
not allies by any stretch of the
imagination
now why has india shifted towards the
u.s because of
it's a natural shift it's a geopolitical
realignment which is bound to happen
india came under increasingly uh severe
heat from the chinese the chinese
economy started growing
and their military power power also grew
uh correspondingly
and the us needed allies to to basically
counter balance china so india happens
to be the natural
ally or pseudo ally or quasi ally
because it is the only significant uh
power in asia that can possibly balance
china or counter china
it's the only power in asia that can do
it
so that's why the indians and the
americans are currently
so to say natural allies but the
americans will never want india to rise
beyond a certain level
so what is the reason for china's
aggression towards india china is
aggressive towards everybody
china doesn't want any large countries
in asia china
wants to see india fragmented and broken
up into lots of different small states
and that has been their policy for many
decades
uh so so that is the reason why the
chinese are aggressive towards
towards india they want to see a
unipolar world only china should be the
hegemon
a unipolar world the only superpower
they want was the u.s destroyed they
want to see every other country
as a client state of china as a vasal of
china
so the best way to do it with india is
to fragment india and that's why
it is extremely aggressive towards india
so that explains the chinese
policy of aggression constant aggression
towards india
okay so man asks should india formally
alive with the us by institutionalizing
the quad like nato
should india make its own alliance with
smaller countries like southeast asian
nations brazil
basically us can can the us be trusted
to help india against china
unconditionally
or is it just using us as a pawn against
china
what is the american national interest
to
ensure that the united states remains
the only superpower
in the only global hegemon and it will
use various
pieces on the chessboard to
counterbalance china
and india is one of those chess pieces
it is not a pawn it is a slightly larger
piece
but it is a chess piece that the us is
uh using to
counter balance china and try to
destabilize possibly
china india is not doing anything to
destabilize china but the us would like
to use india
in the future in in that manner in some
way
so can the us be trusted to help india
the us can be trusted
to pursue its national interest that's
what the u.s can be trusted to do
the u.s cannot be trusted to help
anybody else achieve their own national
interest the us will only pursue its own
national interest
when their national interest converges
with india's national interest
we will work together when it does not
we will not work together
that's how it that's how it works now
what india should do is
what india should do whatever is best
for
its long-term national interest in the
immediate term and then long term and
the medium term
so right now india is basically having a
de facto
quasi alliance with the us and the
so-called quad countries
australia japan india and the us it's
not a formal alliance
it's a lose confederation of sorts there
is no
actual military alliance at all
but it could in the future perhaps go in
the direction depending on how china
behaves
so it's a reactive arrangement it's not
a proactive
arrangement so there is nothing
unconditional in geopolitics
the americans are doing what suits them
best right now our interests ally
what should india do in the long run in
the long run india should emerge as a
global power
on its own right i don't mean that india
should be a hegemonic power
an oppressive power an expansion is
power but india should be secure
in its own strength and india should
have
a significant region of power projection
and various kinds of influence that
exceeds
its current international borders
it should be in a position to rearrange
the geopolitical arrangements
outside beyond its borders so that's
what defines a great power
so that's what india should aspire to
india has everything it needs
to become a great power in in as much as
short as a decade if it wants to
if it can get if it can get its internal
problems right if it can basically
uh get that right you know so that's
what india needs to do that's what i
hope
india does it will be good for the world
india is
not an expansionist power india is a
benevolent power has always been a
benevolent power
so a strong and powerful india would be
good for the entire world overall so
that's what india should aspire to do
but not
in the next 500 years in the next in the
next 10 to 20 years
so that's what i hope happens okay i'm
gonna take a couple of
live questions and then we will wrap up
for the day
i apologize to those of you who have
been asking questions uh
i will try and take a few but as you
understand i hope i can't take all
questions right so
so let me take a couple of questions
all right let me see
give me a minute please um
okay this is by by no name
hello no name is the world suffering
from the outcomes of the great game
earlier in even today only characters of
nations changed as uk became the us
similarly soviets raised china to divert
and distribute enemy efforts
like you say i agree with you to some
extent
the uh great game never ended
the great game is very much a foot even
today
the uk the the british empire
morphed into the american empire the
soviets propped up china the americans
propped up china now the china is the
new
new aspiring superpower the russians too
have a very powerful
military they are one of the hardest
powers in the world
they can project power globally if they
wish to so there is the situation today
so the world is suffering from the
outcome of history right everything is
something that's left over from history
it's not just the outcome of the great
game from 100 years ago
it's the outcome of everything that ever
happened before it's the outcome of
something that happened thousand years
ago
it's the outcome of things that happened
2000 years ago as well
so that's why you have to understand
history
to see how the present-day world came
into being
how it was shaped what are the forces
and
powers that shaped the world why did
they do that what are the agendas
and what are the agendas at play even
today
so yes that's the way we need to
the that's the way we need to to
approach the study
and analysis of geopolitics
okay rohan chaudhary asks do you think
there would be a satellite war during
ww3
by launching missiles as an example well
that
technology it does exist now if there is
a hot war a third world war like you say
or even a regional conflict
you could see satellites being targeted
so the united states has the ability to
uh target satellites the chinese have
this ability
the russians have this ability and the
indians
we the indians have the ability to
destroy satellites using
anti-satellite weapons so let's say in
the future
india and china enter into a conflict
there's a war
limited war of or any war of any kind
maybe there's a blockade in the malacca
strait
maybe there's a naval war after china
conquers taiwan then their military
then their navy is free to come into the
indian ocean so maybe there's a conflict
there
so what they would want to do is they
would want to disable india's naval
satellites
india's reconnaissance satellites india
would also want to disable chinese
military satellites so there could be
this uh
space war in which satellites are taken
out
one one after the other so the the
technology and the capabilities do exist
it's gonna cause a disaster in orbit
an enormous cloud of debris and we will
basically have to
remain an earthbound species if that
happens
because it will cause it'll create
millions of debris in orbit around the
earth
and we won't be able to launch any
rocket
without it crashing into one of this
debris and being destroyed
so that is something i hope doesn't
happen but the potential
is very much there so good question sir
one last question
for today
okay this is the last question for today
please stop asking questions
my friends we'll we'll get we'll take
more in the next episode
so this question says what will happen
if the chicken's neck is cut from india
completely
will india be able to persuade china to
give back its territory
the only way to persuade somebody in
geopolitics
is by using leverage leverage comes in
the form of
power power projection so the first
thing is india should never
allow the chicken neck that connects
okay what's the chicken neck let me just
elaborate what that is in case we don't
know
the chicken neck
let me bring back the satellite image
so this here the siliguri corridor is
called the chicken neck it's a very
small piece of territory
50 kilometers wide at its largest extent
that connects northeast india to the
mainland
of india and i don't understand why we
agreed to the sort of geography
so this is a very disadvantageous
geography it allows
china the opportunity if a war were to
eventuate
to to try and cut this part of
india's geography off so that it can cut
the northeast of india
or from mainland india and then if that
that were to happen then they could even
take over the northeast of india
so this is a very disadvantageous piece
of geography
what india can do in such an eventuality
is take over bangladesh rapidly
and use that to access the rest of the
country northeast of india
so that is one thing we can do from a
military
strategic perspective but the main thing
is we should never allow this to happen
if china does it then how can india
persuade china to give it back
only by military force there is no other
way india can persuade china
to give it back in case the eventuality
happens where china is able to capture
that territory
so it's all about military strength it's
all about force it's all about power
hard power military power and that is
what lies at the very heart of
geopolitics
our nation is respected on the
geopolitical arena
only to the extent to which it has hard
power
soft power is a mirage it's a chimera
it's an illusion
india needs to stop hankering after soft
power the only power that matters
is hard power my friends and that's what
i would like you to take
at the end of this discussion thank you
so much it was a wonderful
very interesting discussion and we will
continue this next week
but from from me for tonight it is
goodbye so i will see you in the next
episode
bye